Guide to the Alpha Phi Alpha Fraternity, Gamma Iota Lambda chapter records CBHM.0031
Center for Brooklyn History
Alpha Phi Alpha Fraternity, Gamma Iota Lambda chapter records
1905-2019
1944-2010
Center for Brooklyn History
Dwyer, Jessy
McKenzie, Andre
CBHM.0031
5.63 Linear Feet in 9 manuscript boxes, one half manuscript box, and one oversize box.
2.47 Gigabytes in 324 files.
The Alpha Phi Alpha Fraternity, Gamma Iota Lambda chapter records consists of of physical organizational files and newsletters, and digital surrogates primarily of photographs but also including event programs, tickets, brochures and obituaries from 1905 to 2019.
Scope and Contents
The Alpha Phi Alpha Fraternity, Gamma Iota Lambda chapter records consists of physical organizational files and newsletters and digital surrogates primarily of photographs but also including event programs, tickets, brochures and obituaries. The organizational files include minutes from Gamma Iota Lambda chapter board meetings; committee reports; national, regional, and chapter correspondence; event invitations; and press releases. The newsletters include Gamma Iota Lamba chapter newsletters and national Alpha Phi Alpha newsletters. The photographs depict Series 3: Photographs, 1905-2010, consists of digital surrogates of photographs depicting fraternity gatherings, awards ceremonies, anniversaries, and meetings on Long Island, in Brooklyn, and other locations.
Historical Note
Alpha Phi Alpha Fraternity, Inc., the first intercollegiate Greek-letter fraternity established for African American men, was founded on December 4, 1906 at Cornell University in Ithaca, New York by seven college men who recognized the need for a strong bond of brotherhood among African descendants in the United States. The fraternity initially served as a study and support group for minority students who faced racial prejudice, both educationally and socially, at Cornell.
The founders, known to their brethren as the 'seven jewels,' along with early leaders of the fraternity, laid a firm foundation for Alpha Phi Alpha's principles of scholarship, fellowship, good character, and the uplifting of humanity. The organization has been interracial since 1945.
Alpha Phi Alpha chapters were established at other colleges and universities, many of them historically Black institutions, soon after the founding at Cornell. The first alumni chapter was established in 1911. The Gamma Iota Lambda Chapter was chartered in Brooklyn in 1945 with the aim of advancing the well-being of Black Brooklynites and established programs to promote education, health and justice in their neighborhoods. Among the membership are attorneys, civic leaders, architects, clergy, educators, physicians, and veterans. Prominent members include Dr. Hobart S. Jarrett (1915-2005), Alton Burton (1925-2018), and Myles A. Paige (1898-1983).
Conditions Governing Access
Open to users without restriction.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Jessy Dwyer and Andre McKenzie on behalf of the Gamma Iota Lambda Chapter of the Alpha Phi Alpha Fraternity, 2024.
Arrangement
This collection is organized into four series:
- Series 1: Organizational files, 1944-2019
- Series 2: Constitutions and by-laws, 1946 - circa 2000
- Series 3: Newsletters, 1955-2012
- Series 4: Photographs, 1905-2010
Existence and Location of Originals
The originals of digitized materials have been retained by the donor.
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
The digitized material in this collection is available on our digital collections portal under the call number prefix ALPH.
Conditions Governing Access
Two files in Series 1: Organizational files are restricted indefinitely because of personally identifiable information. These restrictions are noted on the file level.
Separated Materials
After the relevant articles were photocopied, the full issues of Afro Times and Our Time Press were moved to the Brooklyn Historical Society newspaper collection (ARC.258).
Clubs; African American fraternal organizations; Fraternal organizations -- New York (State) -- Kings County; African Americans; Black-and-white prints (photographs); Programs (documents); Newsletters; Group portraits; Color prints (photographs); Letters; Admission tickets; Brochures; Minutes; Dwyer, Jessy; Alpha Phi Alpha Fraternity; Alpha Phi Alpha Fraternity. Gamma Iota Lambda Chapter (Brooklyn, N.Y.); McKenzie, Andre; Sutton, Ozell, 1925-2015; Broady, Tolly R. (Tolly Rupert), 1917-1986; Ray, Sandy F.; Paige, Myles, -1983; Robeson, Paul, Jr., 1927-2014; Tandy, Vertner W., 1885-1949
- Series 1: Organizational files, 1944-2019
  Arrangement
  This series is in original order, arranged chronologically with special subject files spanning a long period of time at the end of the series.
  Scope and Contents
  Series 1: Organizational files, 1944-2019, includes news clippings, meeting minutes, committee reports, correspondence, orientation books for officers, press releases, scholarship applications, and event invitations related to chapter, regional, and national fraternity business. Correspondence includes thank you notes from members receiving sympathy or get well gifts. Folders title "Initiation info" are mostly invitations to member initiation events, but also include forms filled out by prospective applicants.
  A file on the history of Alpha wives, a biographical file of member and World Trade Center engineer Alton Burton, and a file on general chapter history are at the end of the series.
  Most of the material from the 1940s are photocopies.
  Conditions Governing Access
  Two files in this series are restricted indefinitely because of personally identifiable information. These restrictions are noted on the file level.
  - [News clippings and correspondence], 1944-1946 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Copy of Gamma Iota Lambda fraternity chartering ceremonies program signed by attendees, March 31, 1945
    Existence and Location of Originals
    The original has been retained by the donor.
    Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
    This file is available on our digital collections portal under the call number ALPH_0003.
  - Correspondence, Minutes, 1953-1959 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Paige Dinner, 1955 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Program for Alpha Phi Alpha testimonial dinner, St. George Hotel, November 6, 1955
    This file is available on our digital collections portal under the call number ALPH_0280
  - National, regional, and chapter correspondence, 1956 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Minutes and committee reports, 1956 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Initiation info, 1956 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Page from The Sphinx, August 1956 featuring five Alpha Phi Alpha Fraternity members
    This file is available on our digital collections portal under the call number ALPH_0281.
  - National, regional, and chapter correspondence, 1957 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Minutes and committee reports, 1957 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Initiation info, 1957 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - [Correspondence], 1957-1959 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - [Joseph Johnson 25-year membership certificate], 1958 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - [Directory of the Chapter Officers], circa 1959 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - National, regional, and chapter correspondence, 1958 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Minutes and committee reports, 1958 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Minutes and committee reports, 1959 (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Chapter and outside correspondence, 1959 (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Minutes and committee reports, 1960 (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - National, regional, and chapter correspondence, 1960 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Minutes and committee reports, 1961 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - National, regional, and chapter correspondence, 1961 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - [Directory of members], 1962 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Minutes and committee reports, 1962 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - National, regional, and chapter correspondence, 1962 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Minutes and committee reports, 1963 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - National, regional, and chapter correspondence, 1963 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Minutes and committee reports, 1964 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence, 1964 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - [Minutes and committee reports], 1965 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - [Correspondence], 1965 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Minutes and committee reports, 1966 (Box 2, Folder 13)
  - Correspondence, 1966 (Box 2, Folder 14)
  - Minutes and committee reports, 1967 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Correspondence, 1967 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Minutes and committee reports, 1968 (Box 2, Folder 17)
  - Chapter and external correspondence, 1968 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Minutes and committee reports, 1969 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Chapter and external correspondence, 1969 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Correspondence, 1970 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Minutes and committee reports, 1970-1972 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - [Correspondence], 1975-1977 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Minutes, 1977-1978 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - National, regional, and chapter correspondence, 1977-1978 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Campaign brochure for Herman Washington, 17th State Assembly District, Hempstead, New York, circa 1978
    Existence and Location of Copies
    This file is available on our digital collections portal under the call number ALPH_0046.
  - Minutes, 1979 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - National and regional correspondence, 1979 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Chapter correspondence, 1979 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - [Minutes], 1979 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Command and staff book for members of Gamma Iota Lamba Executive Board, 1979 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Minutes, 1980 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - National, regional, and chapter correspondence, 1980 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Letter from Franklin H. Williams of Phelps Stokes Fund to John P. Rice, Jr., February 22, 1980
    This file is available on our digital collections portal under the call number ALPH_0011.
  - Minutes, 1982 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Chapter documents, 1982 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Ticket to Alpha Wives of Brooklyn & Long Island annual spring luncheon and card party at Queens College, April 24, 1982
    This file is available on our digital collections portal under the call number ALPH_0103.
  - Program for the Alpha wives of Brooklyn & Long Island Gamma Iota Lambda Chapter of the Alpha Phi Alpha Fraternity, Inc. annual spring scholarship luncheon, April 24, 1982
    This file is available on our digital collections portal under the call number ALPH_0111.
  - Memorial service program for Albert A. Edwards at St. Philip's Church, Harlem, April 24, 1982
    This file is available on our digital collections portal under the call number ALPH_0183
  - Minutes, 1983 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - National, chapter, and external correspondence, 1983 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Alpha Phi Alpha Fraternity founders day program, December 4, 1983
    This file is available on our digital collections portal under the call number ALPH_0004.
  - Minutes, 1984 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Chapter correspondence, 1984 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Ticket to the Alpha Wives of Brooklyn & Long Island, Gamma Iota Lambda Chapter of Alpha Phi Alpha Fraternity, Inc. annual spring luncheon and card party, April 28, 1984
    This file is available on our digital collections portal under the call number ALPH_0026.
  - Ticket to Alpha wives of Brooklyn & Long Island annual spring luncheon and card party at Queens College, April 28, 1984
    This file is available on our digital collections portal under the call number ALPH_0114.
  - Minutes, 1985 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Correspondence, 1985 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Program for the Alpha wives of Gamma Iota Lambda Chapter of Alpha Phi Alpha, Fraternity, Inc. scholarship luncheon, card party, April 20, 1985
    This file is available on our digital collections portal under the call number ALPH_0112.
  - Real estate brochure. Information update from the village of Hempstead Urban Renewal Agency, circa 1985
    This file is available on our digital collections portal under the call number ALPH_0045.
  - Minutes, 1986 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence, 1986 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Sheet of lined paper listing eleven founding members of Gamma Iota Lambda charter of Alpha Phi Alpha Fraternity, 1986
    This file is available on our digital collections portal under the call number ALPH_0006.
  - [Meeting minutes and committee reports], 1987 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Minutes, 1987 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - National, regional, and chapter correspondence, 1987 (Box 5, Folder 1)
  - [Correspondence], 1987 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Minutes and committee reports, 1988 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - National, regional, and chapter correspondence, 1988 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Program for reception honoring Richard R. Green, chancellor of New York city public schools, November 10, 1988
    This file is available on our digital collections portal under the call number ALPH_0023
  - Minutes and committee reports, 1989 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - National and regional correspondence, 1989 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Chapter and external correspondence, 1989 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Minutes and committee reports, 1990 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - National, regional, and chapter correspondence, 1990 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Minutes, 1991 (Box 5, Folder 10)
  - National, regional, and chapter correspondence, 1991 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Minutes and committee reports, 1992 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Minutes and general correspondence, 1993-1994 (Box 6, Folder 3-4)
  - Minutes and committee reports, 1995 (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - National, regional, and chapter correspondence, 1995 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Minutes and committee reports, 1996 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - National, regional, and chapter correspondence, 1996 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Minutes, 1997 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Correspondence, 1997 (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Minutes, 1998 (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Correspondence, 1998 (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - Board of Directors meeting, January 1999 (Box 6, Folder 13)
  - Founders Day, 1999 (Box 6, Folder 14)
  - [John M. Williams article for The Sphinx], 1999 (Box 6, Folder 15)
  - Minutes, 1999 (Box 6, Folder 16)
  - National, regional, and chapter correspondence, 1999 (Box 7, Folder 1)
  - [Scholarship application forms], 1999-2017 (Box 10, Folder 9)
    The contents of this folder are restricted indefinitely because of personally identifiable information.
  - Minutes, 2000 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Correspondence, 2000 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Minutes, 2001 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Correspondence, 2001 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Minutes, 2002 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Correspondence, 2002 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - [Sponsorship for Membership form], 2002 (Box 10, Folder 8)
  - Minutes, 2003 (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Correspondence, 2003 (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Minutes, 2004 (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - Correspondence, 2004 (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - Minutes, 2005 (Box 7, Folder 12)
  - Correspondence, 2005 (Box 7, Folder 13)
  - [Minutes and committee reports], 2006 (Box 7, Folder 14)
  - [Event programs], 2006 (Box 7, Folder 15)
  - [Minutes and committee reports], 2007 (Box 8, Folder 1)
  - [Event programs and invitations], 2007 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - [News clippings], 2007 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - [Minutes and committee reports], 2008 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - [Annual dinner dance press release], 2009 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - [Minutes and committee reports], 2010 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - [Teen Health Summit press release], 2010 (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - [Minutes and committee reports], 2011 (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - [Back to School Jamboree event materials], 2011 (Box 8, Folder 9)
  - [New Members Welcome Package], 2011 (Box 8, Folder 10)
  - [Minutes and committee reports], 2012 (Box 8, Folder 11)
  - [Better Making of Men Symposium planning], 2012 (Box 8, Folder 12)
  - [Minutes and committee reports], 2013 (Box 8, Folder 13)
  - [Minutes and committee reports], 2013 (Box 8, Folder 14)
  - [Event invitations and programs], 2013 (Box 8, Folder 15)
  - [Minutes and committee reports], 2014 (Box 8, Folder 16)
  - [News clipping], 2014 (Box 8, Folder 17)
  - [Minutes and committee reports], 2015 (Box 8, Folder 18)
  - [News clipping], 2015 (Box 8, Folder 19)
  - [Minutes and committee reports], 2016-2017 (Box 9, Folder 1-2)
  - [Correspondence], 2017 (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - [72nd Anniversary celebration program], 2017 (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - [Minutes and committee reports], 2018 (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - [Correspondence], 2018 (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - [Event programs], 2018 (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - [Minutes and committee reports], 2019 (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - Alton Burton, 1965-2018 (Box 9, Folder 9)
  - Chapter history, 1946-2018 (Box 9, Folder 10)
  - Alpha Wives, 1949-circa 2005 (Box 9, Folder 11)
  - Brother of the Year, 2014-2015 (Box 9, Folder 12)
- Series 2: Constitutions and by-laws, 1946 - circa 2000
  This series is in original, chronological order.
  Series 2: Constitutions and by-laws, 1946-circa 2000, is made up of booklets containing the constitution and by-laws of the Gamme Iota Lambda chapter of Alpha Phi Alpha. There is also one booklet with the constitution and by-laws of the New York Association of Chapters of Alpha. Some of the documents were sent out to chapter officers for comments and revisions.
  - Constitutions, 1946-1967 (Box 9, Folder 13)
  - Constitutions, 1980-1984 (Box 9, Folder 14)
  - Constitutions, 2005-2016 (Box 9, Folder 15)
  - Constitutions, circa 2017 (Box 9, Folder 16)
  - [Constitution and by-laws for the New York Association of Chapters of Alpha], circa 2000 (Box 9, Folder 17)
- Series 3: Newsletters, 1955-2012
  This series is arranged by newsletter and then in chronological order.
  Series 3: Newsletters, 1955-2012, includes newsletters published at the national, regional, and chapter levels of Alpha Phi Alpha. Newsletters include the Alpha newsletter, published by the Office of the General Secretary; The Alpha Spirit, official newsletter of the Alpha Phi Alpha fraternity; Alpha newsletter, published by the Office of the Executive Director; the Chapter Bulletin: The Newsletter for the Chapters of the Alpha Phi Alpha Fraternity; The Fraternal Spirit, published by the New York Association of Chapters of Alpha; and the Gamma Iota Lambda newsletter.
  - [New York Association of Chapters of Alpha Official Newsletter], 1992 (Box 9, Folder 18)
  - [Alpha Phi Alpha Fraternity newsletters], 1955-1963 (Box 9, Folder 19-20)
  - [Alpha Phi Alpha Fraternity newsletters], 1978-2003 (Box 10, Folder 1-3)
  - Alpha Newsletter, spring 1979
    This file is available on our digital collections portal under the call number ALPH_0283
  - [Gamma Iota Lambda chapter newsletters], 1970-1989 (Box 10, Folder 4-5, Box OS-23)
  - [Gamma Iota Lambda chapter newsletters], 1993-1995 (Box 10, Folder 6)
  - [Gamma Iota Lambda chapter newsletters], 2007-2012 (Box 10, Folder 7)
- Series 4: Photographs, 1905-2010
  Series 3: Photographs, 1905-2010, consists of digital surrogates of photographs depicting fraternity gatherings, awards ceremonies, anniversaries, and meetings on Long Island, in Brooklyn, and other locations. The photographs also depict the gatherings of the Alpha Wives of Brooklyn and Long Island, which raised funds for scholarships.
  Some of the photographs were housed in an album with captions written under the items. In most cases these captions were written by member John R. Rice, Jr. Other photographs had inscriptions on the reverse, or had separate caption documents. All of this information has been added to the item record on CBH's digital collections.
  The files have been assigned call numbers in numerical order in the order in which they were scanned from the donor's files. ALPH_0001 through ALPH_0184 are stored in a photo album and the rest of the materials are stored in two folders.
  The originals have been retained by the donor.
  These files are available on our digital collections portal under the call number prefix ALPH.